A Guide to the National Committee on United States-China Relations records, RG 4, Accession 4 FA1186
Rockefeller Archive Center
National Committee on United States-China Relations records, RG 4, Accession 4
1966-2002
Rockefeller Archive Center
National Committee on United States-China Relations, Inc.
FA1186
25.87 Cubic Feet 61 document boxes, 1 oversized flat box
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
When requesting to view audiovisual material, please refer to the Title and the AV Number (example: AV 1916). Researchers are asked to check the "Restrictions" note for each Title. If a Title does not currently have an access copy, please contact an RAC archivist for further instruction.
Scope and Contents
RG 4 contains records of Exchanges to and from China, mainly from the early 1970s to the mid-1980s, and includes records of the Ping Pong Diplomacy visit of the Chinese table tennis team in 1972. The Conferences, Seminars, Workshops, and Dialogues series includes records of seminars held for the regional press in the 1960s - early 1970s, and early explorations of exchanges with China. Significant materials in other series include Program files relating to educational outreach, such as BAYCEP, the Bay Area China Education Project; and Art and Archaeology files relating to the archaeological exhibit that toured the U. S. from China in 1974-1975.
Biographical / Historical
The National Committee on United States – China Relations (NCUSCR) was established in 1966 as a nonprofit educational organization with a mission to encourage mutual understanding and dialogue between citizens of the United States and China.
The National Committee came into being through the cooperative efforts of scholars and civic, religious, and business leaders who, at a time of mutual hostility between the two countries, sought to stimulate public discussion about China and the United States' relations with it by sponsoring conferences, seminars, publications, and other education and outreach programs. In 1972, the National Committee sponsored the Chinese table tennis team's historic U. S. visit. This round of "Ping Pong Diplomacy," which followed closely on Richard Nixon's visit to China in February 1972, helped pave the way for later exchanges and, eventually, for the normalization of relations with China in 1979. Building on these cultural exchanges, the National Committee came to be a primary organizer of professional and policy exchanges between the two countries (and including Hong Kong and Taiwan), in the areas of foreign affairs and international relations, economic development, governance and legal affairs, education, mass media, environmental and global issues, etc. As its role in exchanges became more prominent, the National Committee turned over some of its educational programs to the Asia Society in the late 1970s, but it continues its educational role through public education events and ongoing outreach.
Funding for the National Committee comes from the United States government (especially the Department of State), corporations, and foundations, as well as from its individual membership.
Arrangement
The records of the National Committee on United States – China Relations are divided into ten record groups, which reflect the order in which the records were received (but which are otherwise an artificial distinction). The records are sorted intellectually into series, which carry over through all record groups, but they have received little or no physical rearrangement. RG 4 of the NCUSCR records is arranged into eight series: 2 - Exchanges - General; 3 - Exchanges to China; 4 - Exchanges from China; 5 - Conferences, Seminars, Workshops, and Dialogues; 7 - Art and Archaeology; 8 - Programs, Projects, and Proposals; 9 - Ping Pong Diplomacy; and 10 - Development.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The National Committee on United States-China Relations donated its records to the Rockefeller Archive Center by deed of gift dated March 27, 2015.
- Exchanges - General, 2
  Scope and Contents
  The Exchanges – General series in RG 4 mainly documents the establishment of a multi-year cooperative program between the U. S. and China in the area of urban planning and design. The program began with the visit of the Urban Design Study Team in the fall of 1981 (the records of this visit are found in Series 4, Exchanges from China).
  - Urban Design Program - Letters regarding Proposed Program, 1980-1981 (Box 41, Folder 402)
  - Urban Design Program - Correspondence with China, 1980-1982 (Box 41, Folder 403)
  - Urban Design Program - Correspondence with Weiming Lu, 1980-1982 (Box 41, Folder 404)
  - Urban Design Program - Working Group Meetings, 1981, 1983 (Box 41, Folder 405)
  - Urban Design Program - Exchanges, 1981-1982 (Box 42, Folder 406)
    Urban Design Study Team from China, 1981 October 28-November 21 (and Sino-American Conference on Urban Development Technology); Historic Preservation Study Team to China, 1982 May 14-June 2.
  - Urban Design Program - NEA Grant Applications and Reports, 1980-1981 (Box 42, Folder 407)
  - Urban Design Program - Fundraising, 1981-1982 (Box 42, Folder 408)
  - Urban Design Program - Papers and Reports, undated, 1981-1982 (Box 42, Folder 409)
    Papers by Bai Demao and Weiming Lu; Report on Urban Design Study Team visit from China, 1981 October-November.
  - Urban Design Program - Joint Center on Urban Design Proposal, 1985 February (Box 42, Folder 410)
  - Urban Design Program - Chinese - American Glossary of Terms, circa 1980 (Box 42, Folder 411)
  - Urban Design - U. S. Urban Planners Delegation Report, 1979-1980, 1982 (Box 42, Folder 412)
  - U.S. - China Relations - Statements, Essays, and Press Releases, 1951, 1954, 1971-1984 (Box 45, Folder 438)
  - U.S. - China Joint Communique (on Taiwan), 1982 August 17 (Box 45, Folder 439)
    Clippings.
  - Defection, 1981-1984 (Box 45, Folder 440)
    Clippings and Press Releases
  - Defection, 1981-1984; FA1186:025 (Box 61)
    4 black and white snapshots of Chinese tennis delegation, dated 1979 August 30.
- Exchanges to China, 3
  The Exchanges to China series in RG 4 documents exchanges mainly from the 1970s to the early 1980s. The exchanges included cultural organizations such as the Philadelphia Orchestra in 1973, the Boston Symphony Orchestra in 1979, and a dance delegation in 1980; sports delegations (Swimming, Track and Field, Gymnastics, Volleyball, and Basketball, 1973-1979); educators (including college presidents, local and state education officials, science educators, and the National Institute of Education), 1973-1981; political representatives and officials (Congressional staff, young politicians, mayors, and governors), 1975-1979, 1983; plus delegations of City Planners (1979) and on World Affairs (1975). The National Committee also sent delegations of its Board members from 1972-1982 (6 visits).
  The Exchanges to China series also includes files on visits to China by U. S. presidents, cabinet officers, and officials, ranging from Henry Kissinger's secret trip to China in 1971 to George W. Bush's visit in 2002. These files consist for the most part of clippings and copies of government documents; there is little or no original content.
  Exchanges files are generally dated by the trip date. The dates do not reflect the exact date range of the contents.
  - Governors' Delegation to China, 1983 December 5-18 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Museum Directors Delegation, 1981 November 24-December 16 (Box 8, Folder 59)
  - Foundation Education Executives Delegation - General, 1981 November 19-December 8 (Box 8, Folder 60)
  - Foundation Education Executives Delegation - Briefing, 1981 November 19-December 8 (Box 8, Folder 61)
  - Foundation Education Executives Delegation - Follow-Up Report, 1981 November 19-December 8 (Box 8, Folder 62)
  - Women's Delegation, 1981 May 17-June 7 (Box 8, Folder 63-64)
  - Science Education Delegation - Namelists and Bios, 1979 June 25-July 12 (Box 8, Folder 65)
  - Science Education Delegation - Background and Planning, 1979 June 25-July 12 (Box 8, Folder 66)
  - Science Education Delegation - Briefing and Debriefing, 1979 June 25-July 12 (Box 9, Folder 67)
  - Science Education Delegation - Briefing and Debriefing, 1979 June 25-July 12; FA1186:005 (Box 61)
    8x10 black and white group photo of delegation with unidentified Chinese colleagues.
  - Science Education Delegation - Itinerary, Thank Yous, and Follow-Up, 1979 June 25-July 12 (Box 9, Folder 68)
  - Science Education Delegation - Report (Planning), 1979 June 25-July 12 (Box 9, Folder 69)
  - Science Education Delegation - Report (First Drafts), 1979 June 25-July 12 (Box 9, Folder 70)
  - Science Education Delegation - Report (Second Drafts), 1979 June 25-July 12 (Box 9, Folder 71)
  - Boston Symphony Orchestra Tour - General, 1979 March 12-20 (Box 9, Folder 72)
  - Boston Symphony Orchestra Tour - Briefing Packet, 1979 March 12-20 (Box 9, Folder 73)
  - Boston Symphony Orchestra Tour - Press Release and Clippings, 1979 March 12-20 (Box 9, Folder 74)
  - Local Education Leaders Delegation - General, 1978 June 22-July 8 (Box 10, Folder 75)
  - Local Education Leaders Delegation - General, 1978 June 22-July 8; FA1186:006 (Box 61)
    4 color Polaroid images of delegates in China.
  - Local Education Leaders Delegation - Background and Planning, 1978 June 22-July 8 (Box 10, Folder 76-77)
  - Local Education Leaders Delegation - Namelists and Bios, 1978 June 22-July 8 (Box 10, Folder 78)
  - Local Education Leaders Delegation - Wrap-Up Meeting (July 8), 1978 June 22-July 8 (Box 10, Folder 79)
  - Local Education Leaders Delegation - Follow-Up, 1978 June 22-July 8 (Box 10, Folder 80)
  - Local Education Leaders Delegation - Debriefing, 1978 June 22-July 8 (Box 10, Folder 81)
    The Debriefing meeting was held September 30 - October 1, 1978.
  - Local Education Leaders Delegation - Report, 1978 June 22-July 8 (Box 11, Folder 82)
  - Local Education Leaders Delegation - Debriefing Kit, 1978 June 22-July 8 (Box 11, Folder 83-84)
    Contains draft of Report sections and Tape Transcripts.
  - Local Education Leaders Delegation - Debriefing Kit (Copy 2), 1978 June 22-July 8 (Box 11, Folder 85)
    Draft of Report sections and Tape Transcripts. Includes some additional edits.
  - Local Education Leaders Delegation - Report (Manuscript Draft), 1978 June 22-July 8 (Box 11, Folder 86)
    File marked "First Drafts."
  - Local Education Leaders Delegation - Report (Manuscript Draft), 1978 June 22-July 8 (Box 12, Folder 87)
    Photocopy of illustrated manuscript of "Children's Palaces: Education in the People's Republic of China as Photographed and Interpreted by American Educators." Marked "Draft #4." Pages 1-296.
  - Local Education Leaders Delegation - Report (Manuscript Draft), 1978 June 22-July 8 (Box 12, Folder 88-90)
    Edited typescript manuscript, with attached photographs, of "Children's Palaces: Education in the People's Republic of China as Photographed and Interpreted by American Educators." Chapters 1-2 (pp. 1-107), 2-3 (pp. 108-211), and 4-5 (pp. 218-285). Includes color photos affixed to manuscript pages.
  - Local Education Leaders Delegation - Report (Extra Photos), 1978 June 22-July 8; FA1186:007 (Box 61)
    Extra photos assembled for Report manuscript. Two captions are missing the photo attachments. Still Image - 37 snapshots, plus 8 captioned images.
  - Women's Volleyball Delegation, 1978 June 13-21 (Box 12, Folder 91)
  - Women's Volleyball Delegation, 1978 June 13-21; FA1186:008 (Box 61)
    Black and white head shots of volleyball team members; 5x7 photos from delegation visit (mounted on report pages).
  - Civic and World Affairs Leaders Delegation, 1978 November 22-December 12 (Box 12, Folder 92)
  - State Education Leaders Delegation - General, 1977 October 28-November 14 (Box 13, Folder 93)
  - State Education Leaders Delegation - Correspondence (Incoming and Outgoing), 1977 October 28-November 14 (Box 13, Folder 94)
  - State Education Leaders Delegation - Invitations, Namelists, and Bios, 1977 October 28-November 14 (Box 13, Folder 95)
  - State Education Leaders Delegation - Wingspread Briefing (1977 September 24-25), 1977 October 28-November 14 (Box 13, Folder 96)
  - State Education Leaders Delegation; Wingspread Debriefing, 1978 February 4-5 (Box 13, Folder 97)
    Includes February 1978 report, "China's Schools in Flux." Delegation trip, 1977 October 28 - November 14.
  - National Committee Board of Directors Delegation - General (3rd Board Delegation), 1977 October 19-November 4 (Box 13, Folder 98)
  - National Committee Board of Directors Delegation - Briefing Packet (3rd Board Delegation), 1977 October 19-November 4 (Box 13, Folder 99)
  - Young Political Leaders Delegation - General, 1977 May 17-June 1 (Box 13, Folder 100)
  - Young Political Leaders Delegation - Background and Planning, 1977 May 17-June 1 (Box 14, Folder 101)
  - Young Political Leaders Delegation - Report and Follow-Up, 1977 May 17-June 1 (Box 14, Folder 102)
  - Gymnastics Delegation - General, 1976 October 26-November 6 (Box 14, Folder 103)
    Trip was postponed from August 1976 because of the Tangshan earthquake.
  - Gymnastics Delegation - Reports and Follow-Up, 1976 October 26-November 6 (Box 14, Folder 104)
  - Congressional Committee Staff Delegation - Background and Planning, 1976 July 26-August 10 (Box 14, Folder 105)
  - Congressional Committee Staff Delegation - Invitations and Bios, 1976 July 26-August 10 (Box 14, Folder 106)
  - Congressional Committee Staff Delegation - Briefing Packet, 1976 July 26-August 10 (Box 14, Folder 107-108)
  - Congressional Committee Staff Delegation - Itinerary, Report, and Follow-Up, 1976 July 26-August 10 (Box 15, Folder 109)
  - World Affairs Delegation - Background and Planning, 1975 October 6-23 (Box 15, Folder 110)
  - World Affairs Delegation - Briefing and Background Mailings, 1975 October 6-23 (Box 15, Folder 111)
  - World Affairs Delegation - Invitations and Bios, 1975 October 6-23 (Box 15, Folder 112)
  - World Affairs Delegation - Meeting Reports, 1975 October 6-23 (Box 15, Folder 113)
  - World Affairs Delegation - Report, 1975 October 6-23 (Box 15, Folder 114)
  - World Affairs Delegation - Follow-Up, 1975 October 6-23 (Box 15, Folder 115)
  - National Committee Delegations - Correspondence, 1972 (Box 15, Folder 116)
  - National Committee Delegations - First Delegation, 1972 December 11-1973 January 6 (Box 15, Folder 117)
  - National Committee Delegations - Second Delegation, 1973 June (Box 15, Folder 118)
  - Educators Delegation - General, 1973 August 1-21 (Box 16, Folder 119)
  - Educators Delegation - Follow-Up, 1973 August 1-21 (Box 16, Folder 120)
  - Swimming and Diving Delegation - General, 1973 June (Box 16, Folder 121)
  - Swimming and Diving Delegation - Schoenfeld, "U.S. A Swim Team to China", 1973 June (Box 16, Folder 122-123)
  - Swimming and Diving Delegation - Fortieth-Anniversary Reunion, 2013 (Box 16, Folder 124)
  - Men's and Women's Basketball Delegation, 1973 June-July (Box 16, Folder 125)
  - Philadelphia Orchestra Tour - General, 1973 September 10-23, 2008 (Box 16, Folder 126)
  - Philadelphia Orchestra Tour - Press Clippings, 1973 September 10-23 (Box 16, Folder 127)
  - Philadelphia Orchestra Tour - Dunn, "Philadelphia Orchestra Experience", 1973 September 10-23 (Box 16, Folder 128)
  - Philadelphia Orchestra Tour - Barber, "Music and Politics - The Philadelphia Orchestra in the People's Republic of China", 1973 September 10-23 (Box 17, Folder 129)
    M.A. thesis by Sue E. Barber.
  - University and College Presidents Delegation - General, 1974 November 8-29 (Box 17, Folder 130)
  - University and College Presidents Delegation - Report, Follow-Up Meeting, and Statement on Exchanges, 1974 November 8-29 (Box 17, Folder 131)
  - University and College Presidents Delegation - Follow-Up Correspondence and Articles, 1974 November 8-29 (Box 17, Folder 132)
  - Track and Field Delegation - General, 1975 May 16-30 (Box 17, Folder 133)
  - Track and Field Delegation - Correspondence and Memos, 1975 May 16-30 (Box 17, Folder 134)
  - Track and Field Delegation - Itinerary and Schedules, 1975 May 16-30 (Box 17, Folder 135)
  - Track and Field Delegation - Non-AAU, 1973-1974 (Box 18, Folder 136)
  - Track and Field Delegation - Press Releases and Coverage, 1975 May 16-30 (Box 18, Folder 137)
  - Track and Field Delegation - Press Releases and Coverage, 1975 May 16-30; FA1186:009 (Box 61)
    8x10 black and white group photo of delegation at airport.
  - Track and Field Delegation - Report and Follow-Up, 1975 May 16-30 (Box 18, Folder 138)
  - Track and Field Delegation - Richard Baum Report, 1975 May 16-30 (Box 18, Folder 139)
  - Mayors Delegation - General (Cancelled), 1975 September 15-29 (Box 18, Folder 140)
  - Mayors Delegation - Booklet, 1975 September 15-29 (Box 18, Folder 141)
  - Mayors Delegation - Cancellation, 1975 September 15-29 (Box 18, Folder 142)
  - City Planners Delegation - Itinerary, Namelists, Background and Planning, 1979 November 25-December 17 (Box 35, Folder 336)
  - City Planners Delegation - Debriefing, 1979 November 25-December 17 (Box 35, Folder 337)
    Debriefing held March 2-4, 1980.
  - City Planners Delegation - Follow-Up Correspondence, 1979 November 25-December 17 (Box 35, Folder 338)
  - City Planners Delegation - Report, 1979 November 25-December 17 (Box 35, Folder 339)
    Urban Planning in China. Report of the U. S. Urban Planners Delegation to the PRC.
  - U.S. National Men's Basketball Team Visit, 1979 April 7-17 (Box 35, Folder 340-341)
  - U.S. National Men's Basketball Team Visit, 1979 April 7-17; FA1186:041 (Box 62)
    Oversized: 4 issues of Tiyu Bao, 1979 April 9, 11, 15 (articles on basketball) and 1979 February 7 (relevant articles not identified).
  - Mayors Delegation - General, 1979 June 16-29 (Box 35, Folder 342)
  - Mayors Delegation - Report, 1979 June 16-29 (Box 35, Folder 343)
    Report by Elizabeth J. Perry. File also includes reports on meetings in Beijing and Shanghai and related articles.
  - Governors Delegation - General, 1979 October 15-28 (Box 35, Folder 344)
    Includes background and planning for trip originally planned for March 1978.
  - Governors Delegation - Report and Follow-Up, 1979 October 15-28 (Box 35, Folder 345)
  - Governors Delegation (Postponed), 1981 October (Box 36, Folder 346)
    Trip postponed.
  - Dance Study Delegation - General, 1980 November 18-December 10 (Box 41, Folder 400)
    Trip sponsored by the U. S. International Communications Agency (USICA).
  - Dance Study Delegation - General, 1980 November 18-December 10; FA1186:023 (Box 61)
    8x10 portrait photos of 5 delegation members.
  - Dance Study Delegation - Background and Planning, 1980 November 18-December 10 (Box 41, Folder 401)
  - National Committee Board Delegation, 1979 (Box 45, Folder 441)
  - National Committee Board Delegation, 1980 November 16-December 2 (Box 45, Folder 442)
  - National Committee Board Delegation, 1982 November 8-23 (Box 45, Folder 443)
  - President George W. Bush Visit, 2002 February (Box 46, Folder 444)
  - Secretary of Defense Colin Powell Visits, 2001-2002 (Box 46, Folder 445)
  - President George W. Bush Visit, APEC Meeting, Shanghai, 2001 October 17-21 (Box 46, Folder 446)
    Asia-Pacific Economic Cooperation.
  - President George W. Bush Visit, APEC Meeting, Shanghai, 2001 October 17-21; FA1186:045 (Box 62)
    Asia-Pacific Economic Cooperation. Oversized: APEC Today supplements, 2001 October 18-19 (2 issues) (Newsletter published by China Secretariat for APEC 2001 and China Daily. Issue nos. 10-11).
  - Visits by U.S. Officials, 2000-2001 (Box 46, Folder 447)
    Secretary of Defense William Cohen, July; Secretary of Agriculture Dan Glickman, April; Congressman Matt Salmon, and Senators Tim Hutchinson, Susan Collins, and Michael Enzi visits to Taiwan, January; Congressman Sander Levin, January.
  - Visits by U. S. Officials, 1999 March (Box 46, Folder 448)
    Secretary of State Madeleine Albright; Secretary of Defense William Perry.
  - Visits by U.S. Officials, 1998 (Box 46, Folder 449)
    Congressman Bobby Etheridge visit to Taiwan, December; Secretary of Defense William Cohen, January.
  - President William J. Clinton Visit, 1998 June (Box 46, Folder 450-452)
  - Visits by U. S. Officials, 1997 (Box 46, Folder 453)
    Secretary of Commerce William Daley, October; Chief of Naval Operations Admiral Jay L. Johnson, October; Treasury Secretary Robert Rubin, September; Secretary of State Madeleine Albright, February.
  - Speaker of the House Newt Gingrich Visit, 1997 March (Box 46, Folder 454)
  - Vice President Albert Gore Visit, 1997 March (Box 47, Folder 455)
  - Visits by U. S. Officials, 1995-1996 (Box 47, Folder 456)
    1996: Secretary of State Warren Christopher, November; CIA Director John Deutch, October; Anthony Lake, National Security Advisor, July; Senators Dianne Feinstein, Sam Nunn, and John Glenn, January. 1995: Jeffrey Garten, Undersecretary of Commerce for International Trade, April; Energy Secretary Hazel O'Leary, February; Justice Anthony Kennedy, February 7-13; Assistant Secretary of State for Human Rights John Shattuck, January.
  - Visits by U. S. Officials, 1994 (Box 47, Folder 457)
    Secretary of Defense William Perry, October; Commerce Secretary Ronald H. Brown, August; Secretary of State Warren Christopher, March.
  - Former President Richard M. Nixon Visit, 1989 October (Box 47, Folder 458)
  - President George H. W. Bush Visit, 1989 February (Box 47, Folder 459)
  - Secretary of State George P. Schultz Visit, 1987 August (Box 47, Folder 460)
  - President Ronald Reagan Visit to China, 1984 April (Box 47, Folder 461)
    Paper and clippings.
  - Secretary of State George P. Schultz Visit to China, 1983 February (Box 47, Folder 462)
    Clippings
  - Secretary of State Alexander Haig Visit to China, 1981 June 14-16 (Box 47, Folder 463)
  - Secretary of Defense Harold Brown's Visit to China, 1980 January (Box 47, Folder 464)
    Clipping
  - President Richard M. Nixon's First Visit to China, 1972 February (Box 47, Folder 465)
    February, 1972 Redux. A look back at President Nixon's trip to China?.
  - President Richard M. Nixon's First Visit to China (Nixon - Zhou Enlai Talks), 1972 February (Box 47, Folder 466)
  - Henry Kissinger's Secret Trip to China, 1970 September-1971 July (Box 47, Folder 467)
  - UNICEF Delegation, 1980 March 31-April 15 (Box 52, Folder 513)
  - National Institute of Education Delegation - General, 1980 October 2-18 (Box 53, Folder 516)
  - National Institute of Education Delegation - Translations, 1980 October 2-18 (Box 53, Folder 517)
    Translations into English of papers by Chinese authors.
  - National Institute of Education Delegation - Report Drafts, 1980 October 2-18 (Box 53, Folder 518)
  - National Institute of Education Delegation - Report Papers and Drafts, 1980 October 2-18 (Box 53, Folder 519)
- Exchanges from China, 4